In ZOS Unix, pipes are a communication mechanism for sending arrays of data between two processes.
Pipes are conceptually like a sequential file.
Processes can write into a pipe and other processes can read from the pipe.
Pipes exist only during the time they're open.
The storage needed for the pipes is obtained from a data space associated with the kernel address space.
And there are two types of pipes.
Unnamed pipes are used between related processes, so for example between a parent and a child process.
An unnamed pipe is created by the pipe function.
The pipe function also opens the pipe to use.
No security checking is performed on unnamed pipes since they are available only to a process and its children.
And there's also named pipes which are also called FIFO.
A FIFO resides in the hierarchical file system and can be referenced by a name.
Thus, they can be used for communication between any two processes.
Once processes are created, there are many ways to communicate between them.
We've already talked about pipes being the most common way.
Other ways include wait and execute.
A parent process can wait on the exit of a child.
Signals.
One process can send a system or user signal to another.
The receiving process should be coded to receive and process the signal.
There's shared memory.
Since processes run in different address spaces, these services can be used to define specific memory to be shared.
The kernel will keep these pages in a shared data space.
Message queues.
This is a technique similar to piping but with the capability of reading and writing a message at a time rather than a string of characters.
The kernel also uses a shared data space for these messages.
And there's semaphores, which are used to control the use of shared memory by multiple processes.
They are kept in the kernel process.
The ZOS Unix interprocess communication or IPC functions are shared memory, message queues and semaphores.
Users can invoke applications that create IPC resources and wait for IPC resources.
IPC resources are not released when a process terminates or a user logs off.
Therefore, it is possible that an IPC user might need assistance to remove an IPC resource using the Shell's ipcrm command.
The ipcs shell command can be used to display the IPC resources in a system,
which users own the resources and which users are waiting for a resource.
Frequently used ZOS Unix programs can be placed into the ZOS link pack area or the LPA to improve performance.
The Shell's a good candidate for that because only one copy of it can be used by all requesters, saving space in IO.
When searching for a program with the sticky bit on, ZOS Unix will look in the user's step line,
the link pack area and the link list concatenation.
In order to keep a ZOS Unix program in, LPA, a number of things must be done.
The file in the hierarchical file system that contains the program must have the sticky bit set by an authorized user.
The sticky bit can also be set on a directory level.
It limits removing or renaming subdirectories or files to the owner or the super user.
Also, the program must be link edited and placed in sys1.lpalib or a dataset in LPA list.
The program is copied to LPA during the next IPL.
Threads provide support for multiple separate units of dispatchable work within a process.
A ZOS Unix thread can be compared with a ZOS task.
The thread support allows application programmers to develop multitasking server applications
that require multiple concurrent execution streams.
A program using threads can have significant performance benefits in a multiprocessor environment
where each thread in the process can run on an individual processor.
Threads are created with the pthread underscore create c function.
Since threads share address space, there are services to protect the memory of the address space
and to synchronize the execution of the threads.
These are mutex, which is a structure associated with the variable,
and used by threads to determine if a variable is in use,
and condition variable used to synchronize the execution of the activities of the threads.
So what are some of the differences between ZOS tasks and POSIX threads?
ZOS has a task hierarchy.
POSIX threads have no hierarchy except for the initial thread which behaves differently from the other threads.
ZOS tasks usually run different programs.
All POSIX threads in a process run the same program.
ZOS tasks can be independent or cooperating.
POSIX threads must cooperate, they do not operate independently.
ZOS allocates storage at task level, and some storage can be shared between tasks and some not.
The programs can be located in common storage, CSA or LPA,
in private area below the 16 megabyte line, or in private area above the 16 megabyte line.
All POSIX threads in a process share all storage allocated to the process.
Now, this diagram shows the ZOS program management functions
and the equivalent functions in ZOS Unix.
Some of these similarities include that programs can reside in different libraries
and there is an automatic search to locate them.
Both interfaces provide a method to replace the current executing program with a new program.
And both sets of interfaces have ways to create work in separate address spaces.
But there are also many differences, including with tasks, load and program execution.
And that's it for ZOS Unix functions.
In the next module, we'll look at working with the ZOS Unix environment.